Guide to the Hartley Simpson Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Hartley Simpson papers
1939-1964
MS 451
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
(1 box)
The papers consist of correspondence, research notes on graduate education, and essays.
Simpson, Hartley, 1900-1967
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Elizabeth Read Foster, 1990.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Hartley Simpson Papers consist of correspendence, research notes on graduate education, and essays which Hartley Simpson intended for a "Sketch-Book." The essays do not necessarily pertain to historical topics.
The papers were received from Elizabeth Read Foster in 1990.
Biographical / Historical
Hartley Simpson was born in Tilton, New Hampshire in 1900. He received his B.A. degree from Bowdoin College in 1922 and was a student at Cornell University from 1923-1926. Simpson was an assistant professor of history at the University of Pittsburgh from 1926-1929. He spent the remainder of his career at Yale University and held the positions of research assistant in history (1930-1942), research associate (1942-1946), and associate professor (1947-1967). Simpson was also assistant dean of the Graduate School (1942-1947), associate dean (1947-1956), and dean (1956-1961). He died on October 4, 1967.
Universities and colleges -- Graduate work; Simpson, Hartley, 1900-1967; Yale University -- Graduate work; Yale University. Graduate School
- Inventory
  - Correspondence, 1948 December 7, 1959 March 31, 1960-1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Essays for "Sketch Book", December 1961 - December 1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Essays for "Sketch Book", January 1963 - March 1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Essays for "Sketch Book", May 1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Essays for "Sketch Book", undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Essays labelled "Case Book", undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Unsorted essays, 1961, 1964,undated (Box 1, Folder 7 - 8)
  - Writings pertaining to graduate schools, 1956, 1962,undated (Box 1, Folder 9 - 10)
  - Yale graduate school information, 1940 - 1960, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Research notes pertaining to education and graduate schools, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Printed material and news clippings, 1949 - 1963, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Material sent to Hartley Simpson from George Frederick Gundelfinger, 1939 - 1963, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)